I once said,
لقد قلت فيما مضى،
"If you want to liberate a society,
"إذا أردت تحرير مجتمع،
all you need is the Internet."
كل ما تحتاجه هو الإنترنت."
I was wrong.
لقد كنت مخطئا.
I said those words back in 2011,
قلت ذلك في عام 2011،
when a Facebook page I anonymously created
عندما ساعدت صفحة فيس بوك قمت بإنشائها
helped spark the Egyptian revolution.
خفية في إشعال الثورة المصرية.
The Arab Spring revealed social media's greatest potential,
عرض الربيع العربي أفضل إمكانيات مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي،
but it also exposed its greatest shortcomings.
لكنه أيضا كشف أكبر قصور له.
The same tool that united us to topple dictators
نفس الأدوات التي وحّدتنا لقلب الدكتاتوريات
eventually tore us apart.
في نهاية المطاف هي التي فرقتنا.
I would like to share my own experience in using social media for activism,
أرغب في تشارك تجربتي في استخدام مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي للحراك،
and talk about some of the challenges I have personally faced
وأتحدث عن بعض التحديات التي واجهتها شخصيا
and what we could do about them.
وماذا يمكننا أن نفعل حيالها.
In the early 2000s,
في بواكير الألفية الجديدة،
Arabs were flooding the web.
كان العرب يغمرون الشبكة العنكبوتية.
Thirsty for knowledge, for opportunities,
عطشى لأجل المعرفة، والفرص،
for connecting with the rest of the people around the globe,
والتواصل مع بقية الناس حول العالم،
we escaped our frustrating political realities
لقد هربنا من واقعنا السياسي المحبط
and lived a virtual, alternative life.
وعشنا حياة افتراضية بديلة.
Just like many of them, I was completely apolitical until 2009.
تماما مثل كثيرين، لم أكن سياسيا حتى عام 2009.
At the time, when I logged into social media,
في الوقت الذي تسجلت في مواقع التواصل الاجتماعي،
I started seeing more and more Egyptians
بدأت أرى مصريين أكثر وأكثر
aspiring for political change in the country.
يتوقون للتغيير السياسي في البلاد.
It felt like I was not alone.
وشعرت بأنني لست وحدي.
In June 2010,
في يونيو 2010،
Internet changed my life forever.
غيّرت الإنترنت حياتي إلى الأبد.
While browsing Facebook,
بينما كنت أتصفح الفيس بوك،
I saw a photo, a terrifying photo, of a tortured, dead body
رأيت صوة، صورة بشعة، لجثة تم تعذيب صاحبها
of a young Egyptian guy.
وهو شاب مصري يافع.
His name was Khaled Said.
كان اسمه خالد سعيد.
Khaled was a 29-year-old Alexandrian who was killed by police.
كان خالد من الإسكندرية وعمره 29 عاما تم قتله من قبل الشرطة.
I saw myself in his picture.
لقد رأيت نفسي في صورته.
I thought, "I could be Khaled."
وقلت لنفسي، "كان من الممكن أن أكون خالد."
I could not sleep that night, and I decided to do something.
لم أستطع النوم في تلك الليلة، وقررت أن أفعل شيئا.
I anonymously created a Facebook page
في الخفاء قمت بإنشاء صفحة فيس بوك
and called it "We are all Khaled Said."
وأطلقت عليها " كلنا خالد سعيد."
In just three days, the page had over 100,000 people,
وخلال 3 أيام أعجب بالصفحة أكثر من 100 ألف شخص،
fellow Egyptians who shared the same concern.
مواطنون مصريون كان لديهم نفس المخاوف.
Whatever was happening had to stop.
بأن ما يحدث ينبغي أن يتوقف.
I recruited my co-admin, AbdelRahman Mansour.
وقمت بتعيين زميلي عبدالرحمن منصور مديرا للصفحة معي.
We worked together for hours and hours.
عملنا معا لساعات وساعات.
We were crowdsourcing ideas from the people.
كنا نحشد الأفكار من الناس.
We were engaging them.
ونجعل الناس يشاركون.
We were calling collectively for actions,
وكنا ننادي بالتحرك مجتمعين،
and sharing news that the regime did not want Egyptians to know.
ونتشارك الأخبار التي لا يريد النظام أن يعرفها المصريون.
The page became the most followed page
وأصبحت الصفحة أكثر الصفحات متابعة
in the Arab world.
في العالم العربي.
It had more fans than established media organizations
وحصلت على إعجاب أكثر من المؤسسات الإعلامية المرموقة
and even top celebrities.
وحتى أشهر النجوم.
On January 14, 2011,
في 14 يناير 2011،
Ben Ali fled out of Tunisia
هرب بن علي من تونس
after mounting protests against his regime.
بعد احتدام المظاهرات ضد نظامه.
I saw a spark of hope.
رأيت ومضة الأمل.
Egyptians on social media were wondering,
تعجّب المصريون على صفحات التواصل الاجتماعي
"If Tunisia did it, why can't we?"
"إذا فعلتها تونس، لم لا نستطيع نحن؟"
I posted an event on Facebook and called it
قمت بوضع حدث على الفيس بوك وأسميته
"A Revolution against Corruption, Injustice and Dictatorship."
"ثورة ضد الفساد والظلم والديكتاتورية."
I posed a question to the 300,000 users of the page at the time:
وطرحت سؤالا على 300،000 من رواد الصفحة حينئذ:
"Today is the 14th of January.
اليوم هو الرابع عشر من يناير
The 25th of January is Police Day.
ويوم 25 هو يوم الشرطة.
It's a national holiday.
إنها إجازة قومية.
If 100,000 of us take to the streets of Cairo,
إذا قام 100 ألف منا بالتظاهر في شوارع القاهرة،
no one is going to stop us.
لن يستطيع أحد إيقافنا.
I wonder if we could do it."
أتساءل إن كنا نستطيع فعل ذلك."
In just a few days, the invitation reached over a million people,
في أيام قلائل، وصلت الدعوة لأكثر من مليون شخص،
and over 100,000 people confirmed attendance.
وأكّد أكثر من 100 ألف شخص حضورهم.
Social media was crucial for this campaign.
كانت وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي مهمة لهذه الحملة.
It helped a decentralized movement arise.
لقد ساعدت في قيام حركة لا مركزية.
It made people realize that they were not alone.
وجعلت الناس يدركون بأنهم ليسوا لوحدهم.
And it made it impossible for the regime to stop it.
وجعلت من المستحيل إيقافها من قبل النظام.
At the time, they didn't even understand it.
حينها، لم يفهموا الأمر حتى.
And on January 25th, Egyptians flooded the streets of Cairo and other cities,
وفي 25 يناير، تدفق المصريون على شوارع القاهرة والمدن الأخرى،
calling for change,
منادين بالتغيير،
breaking the barrier of fear
وكاسرين لحاجز الخوف
and announcing a new era.
ومعلنين عن حقبة جديدة.
Then came the consequences.
بعدها جاءت التبعات.
A few hours before the regime cut off the Internet and telecommunications,
قبل ساعات من قطع النظام للإنترنت والاتصالات،
I was walking in a dark street in Cairo, around midnight.
كنت أمشي في شارع مظلم في القاهرة، حوالي منتصف الليل.
I had just tweeted, "Pray for Egypt.
وقمت بتغريدة، " أدعوا لمصر.
The government must be planning a massacre tomorrow."
لابد وأن الحكومة تخطط لمجزرة غدا."
I was hit hard on my head.
تم ضربي بشدة على رأسي.
I lost my balance and fell down,
ففقدت توازني وسقطت على الأرض،
to find four armed men surrounding me.
لأجد 4 رجال مسلحين يحيطون بي.
One covered my mouth and the others paralyzed me.
غطى أحدهم فمي وقام الآخرون بشلّ حركتي.
I knew I was being kidnapped by state security.
عرفت أنه يجري خطفي بواسطة أمن الدولة.
I found myself in a cell,
وجدت نفسي في زنزانة،
handcuffed, blindfolded.
مكبل اليدين، معصوب العينين.
I was terrified.
شعرت بالرعب.
So was my family,
وكذلك أسرتي،
who started looking for me
الذين بدأوا بالبحث عني
in hospitals, police stations and even morgues.
في المستشفيات، مراكز الشرطة وحتى المشارح.
After my disappearance,
بعد اختفائي،
a few of my fellow colleagues who knew I was the admin of the page
قليل من زملائي الذين يعلمون بأنني مدير في الصفحة،
told the media about my connection with that page,
أخبروا وسائل الإعلام بصلتي بتلك الصفحة،
and that I was likely arrested by state security.
وأنه من المحتمل أن أمن الدولة قد اعتقلني
My colleagues at Google started a search campaign trying to find me,
قام زملائي في غوغل بحملة بحث محاولين العثور علي،
and the fellow protesters in the square demanded my release.
وطالب زملائي المتظاهرون في الميدان بإطلاق سراحي.
After 11 days of complete darkness,
وبعد 11 يوما من العتمة الشديدة،
I was set free.
تم إطلاق سراحي.
And three days later,
وبعد 3 أيام ،
Mubarak was forced to step down.
أُجبر مبارك على الاستقالة.
It was the most inspiring and empowering moment of my life.
لقد كانت أكثر اللحظات إلهاما في حياتي.
It was a time of great hope.
لقد كانت لحظة أمل عظيم.
Egyptians lived a utopia for 18 days during the revolution.
عاش المصريون في المدينة الفاضلة ل18 يوما خلال الثورة.
They all shared the belief
لقد تشاركوا جميعا الإيمان
that we could actually live together despite our differences,
بأننا يمكن أن نعيش سويا رغما عن الاختلافات،
that Egypt after Mubarak would be for all.
وأن مصر بعد مبارك ستكون للجميع.
But unfortunately,
لكن لسوء الحظ،
the post-revolution events were like a punch in the gut.
أحداث ما بعد الثورة كانت مثل اللكمة في المعدة.
The euphoria faded,
تلاشت النشوة ،
we failed to build consensus,
لقد فشلنا في بناء توافق،
and the political struggle led to intense polarization.
وقاد الصراع السياسي إلى استقطاب حاد.
Social media only amplified that state,
وضخّمت وسائل التواصل تلك الحالة
by facilitating the spread of misinformation, rumors,
بتسهيل انتشار التضليل والشائعات،
echo chambers and hate speech.
غرف الصدى الإعلامية و خطاب الكراهية.
The environment was purely toxic.
كانت البيئة سامة حقا.
My online world became a battleground filled with trolls, lies, hate speech.
وأصبح عالمي الرقمي ساحة للقتال مليئة بالمتصيدين، الكاذبين وبأحاديث الكراهية.
I started to worry about the safety of my family.
بدأت بالقلق حيال سلامة أسرتي.
But of course, this wasn't just about me.
لكن بالطبع لم يكن الأمر متعلقا بي فقط.
The polarization reached its peak between the two main powers --
وصل الاستقطاب ذروته بين القوتين الرئيسيتيين --
the army supporters and the Islamists.
مناصرو الجيش والإسلاميون.
People in the center, like me,
أمثالي، من هم في الوسط،
started feeling helpless.
بدأوا يشعرون بقلة الحيلة.
Both groups wanted you to side with them;
يريدك الطرفان في جانبهما.
you were either with them or against them.
أنت إما معهم أو أنك ضدهم.
And on the 3rd of July 2013,
وفي الثالث من يوليو 2013،
the army ousted Egypt's first democratically elected president,
أطاح الجيش بأول رئيس مصري تم انتخابه ديموقراطيا،
after three days of popular protest that demanded his resignation.
بعد مظاهرات عارمة لـ 3 أيام طالبت باستقالته.
That day I made a very hard decision.
في ذلك اليوم أخذت قرارا صعبا.
I decided to go silent, completely silent.
قررت أن التزم بالصمت، تماما.
It was a moment of defeat.
لقد كانت لحظة انهزام.
I stayed silent for more than two years,
بقيت صامتا لأكثر من عامين،
and I used the time to reflect on everything that happened,
واستخدمت الوقت للتفكير حول كل ما جرى،
trying to understand why did it happen.
محاولا فهم لماذا جرى.
It became clear to me
أصبح الأمر واضحا بالنسبة لي
that while it's true that polarization is primarily driven
بأنه بينما يُساق الاستقطاب في الأساس
by our human behavior,
بواسطة غريزتنا البشرية،
social media shapes this behavior and magnifies its impact.
تشكّل وسائل التواصل هذا السلوك وتعظّم من تأثيره.
Say you want to say something that is not based on a fact,
لنقل أنك تريد قول شيء ليس مبنيا على حقائق،
pick a fight or ignore someone that you don't like.
تتعارك أو تتجاهل شخص لا تحبه.
These are all natural human impulses,
كل هذه دوافع بشرية،
but because of technology,
لكن بسبب التكنولوجيا،
acting on these impulses is only one click away.
فالتفاعل بناء على هذه الدوافع هو مجرد نقرة على الفأرة.
In my view, there are five critical challenges
في وجهة نظري، هناك خمس تحديات رئيسية
facing today's social media.
تواجه وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي الآن.
First, we don't know how to deal with rumors.
أولا، لا نعرف كيف نتعامل مع الشائعات.
Rumors that confirm people's biases
الشائعات التي تؤكد تحيّز الناس
are now believed and spread among millions of people.
يتم تصديقها الآن وتنتشر بين ملايين الناس
Second, we create our own echo chambers.
ثانيا، نحن نخلق غرف أصدائنا.
We tend to only communicate with people that we agree with,
نحن نميل للتواصل مع الناس الذين يتفقون معنا،
and thanks to social media,
وبفضل وسائل التواصل،
we can mute, un-follow and block everybody else.
يمكننا إخراس، وعدم متابعة ومنع أي شخص آخر.
Third, online discussions quickly descend into angry mobs.
ثالثا، تنحدر النقاشات على الإنترنت بسرعة إلى الجماهير الغاضبة.
All of us probably know that.
ربما يعلم جميعنا بذلك.
It's as if we forget
الأمر كما لو أننا ننسى
that the people behind screens are actually real people
أن الناس خلف الشاشات هم في الحقيقة بشر
and not just avatars.
ليسوا مجرد أقنعة.
And fourth, it became really hard to change our opinions.
ورابعا، أصبح من الصعب جدا أن نغيّر آراءنا.
Because of the speed and brevity of social media,
بسبب سرعة و إيجاز التواصل الاجتماعي،
we are forced to jump to conclusions
نحن مجبرون على القفز إلى الخلاصات
and write sharp opinions in 140 characters
وكتابة رأي صارم في 140 حرفا
about complex world affairs.
حول شؤون العالم المعقدة.
And once we do that, it lives forever on the Internet,
وبمجرد فعلنا لذلك، يدوم الأمر إلى الأبد على الإنترنت،
and we are less motivated to change these views,
ونصبح أقل حماسا لتغيير هذه الآراء،
even when new evidence arises.
حتى عندما تظهر أدلة جديدة .
Fifth -- and in my point of view, this is the most critical --
خامسا -- وفي رأيي، هذه الأكثر أهمية --
today, our social media experiences are designed in a way
تجاربنا في وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي صُممت بطريقة
that favors broadcasting over engagements,
تُفضّل النشر على المشاركة،
posts over discussions,
تُفضّل المنشورات على النقاشات،
shallow comments over deep conversations.
والتعليقات السطحية مقابل النقاشات العميقة.
It's as if we agreed that we are here to talk at each other
يبدو الأمركما لو أننا اتفقنا أننا هنا لنتحدث لبعضنا البعض
instead of talking with each other.
عوضا عن الحديث مع بعضنا البعض.
I witnessed how these critical challenges contributed
لقد شهدت كيف ساهمت هذه التحديات الخطيرة
to an already polarized Egyptian society,
في استقطاب المجتمع المصري المُستقطب في الأصل،
but this is not just about Egypt.
لكن الأمر ليس فقط حول مصر.
Polarization is on the rise in the whole world.
الإستقطاب في ازدياد في كل العالم.
We need to work hard on figuring out
نحن بحاجة للعمل بجد لنعرف
how technology could be part of the solution,
كيف يمكن للتكنولوجيا أن تكون جزء من الحل
rather than part of the problem.
عوضا عن كونها جزء من المشكلة.
There's a lot of debate today on how to combat online harassment
هناك الكثير من الجدل الآن حول محاربة التحرش الرقمي
and fight trolls.
ومحاربة المتصيدين.
This is so important.
هذه مهم للغاية.
No one could argue against that.
لا يمكن لشخص أن يجادل حول ذلك.
But we need to also think about how to design social media experiences
لكننا أيضا بحاجة للتفكير حول كيفية تصميم تجارب تواصل اجتماعي
that promote civility and reward thoughtfulness.
تعزز الكيّاسة وتكافؤ التفكير العميق.
I know for a fact
أعلم يقينا
if I write a post that is more sensational,
أنني إذا كتبت منشورا مليئا بالإثارة،
more one-sided, sometimes angry and aggressive,
أحادي الرأي، و بعض الأحيان غاضبا وقاسيا،
I get to have more people see that post.
سأحصل على مشاهدات أكثر لذلك المنشور
I will get more attention.
سأحصل على مزيد من الاهتمام.
But what if we put more focus on quality?
لكن ماذا لو وضعنا تركيزا أكثر على الجودة؟
What is more important:
ما هو المهم:
the total number of readers of a post you write,
عدد قُراء المنشور الذي كتبته،
or who are the people who have impact that read what you write?
أم من هم الأشخاص ذوو التأثير الذين يقرؤون ما تكتب؟
Couldn't we just give people more incentives to engage in conversations,
هل يمكننا تقديم حوافز أكثر للناس لإشراكهم في الحوارات،
rather than just broadcasting opinions all the time?
بدلا من نشر الآراء طوال الوقت؟
Or reward people for reading
أو مكافأة الناس على القراءة
and responding to views that they disagree with?
والرد على وجهات النظر التي تخالف قناعاتهم؟
And also, make it socially acceptable that we change our minds,
وأيضا، نجعل من المقبول اجتماعيا تغيير وجهات نظرنا،
or probably even reward that?
أو ربما المكافأة عن ذلك؟
What if we have a matrix that says how many people changed their minds,
ماذا لو كانت لدينا مصفوفة توضح عدد الناس الذين غيروا وجهات نظرهم،
and that becomes part of our social media experience?
ويصبح ذلك جزء من تجربتنا في وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي؟
If I could track how many people are changing their minds,
إذا استطعت تتبع عدد الناس الذين يغيّرون آرائهم،
I'd probably write more thoughtfully, trying to do that,
من المحتمل أن أكتب بعمق أكثر، أحاول فعل ذلك،
rather than appealing to the people who already agree with me
بدلا من مناشدة الذين يتفقون معي بالفعل
and "liking" because I just confirmed their biases.
ويعجبهم لأنني فقط قمت بتأكيد تحيزاتهم.
We also need to think about effective crowdsourcing mechanisms,
نحن أيضا نحتاج للتفكير بفاعلية آليات التعهيد الجماعي،
to fact-check widely spread online information,
لنتأكد من حقيقة المعلومات المنشورة على الانترنت،
and reward people who take part in that.
ونقوم بمكافأة الذين يشاركون في ذلك.
In essence, we need to rethink today's social media ecosystem
جوهر الأمر، أننا بحاجة لإعادة التفكير في بيئة التواصل الاجتماعي الحالية
and redesign its experiences
ونعيد تصميم تجاربها
to reward thoughtfulness, civility and mutual understanding.
لنكافأ التفكير العميق، الكياسة والفهم المتبادل.
As a believer in the Internet, I teamed up with a few friends,
كمؤمن بالإنترنت، انضممت لفريق مع قليل من الأصدقاء،
started a new project,
وبدأنا مشروعا جديدا،
trying to find answers and explore possibilities.
نحاول العثور على إجابات واستكشاف الإمكانيات.
Our first product is a new media platform for conversations.
أول منتج لنا هو منصة إعلامية جديدة للنقاشات.
We're hosting conversations that promote mutual understanding
نحن نستضيف النقاشات التي تروّج للفهم المتبادل
and hopefully change minds.
ونأمل بأن تغيّر العقول.
We don't claim to have the answers,
نحن لا ندّعي أن لدينا الإجابات،
but we started experimenting with different discussions
لكننا بدأنا بتجربتها مع نقاشات مختلفة
about very divisive issues,
حول موضوعات خلافية جدا،
such as race, gun control, the refugee debate,
مثل العرق، التحكم بالأسلحة، جدل المهاجرين،
relationship between Islam and terrorism.
العلاقة بين الإسلام والإرهاب.
These are conversations that matter.
هذه هي النقاشات التي تهم.
Today, at least one out of three people on the planet
اليوم، على الأقل واحد من كل 3 أشخاص على هذا الكوكب
have access to the Internet.
لديه اتصال بالإنترنت.
But part of this Internet is being held captive
لكن جزء من هذا الإنترنت أسير
by the less noble aspects of our human behavior.
بجوانب أقل نبلا من السلوك البشري.
Five years ago, I said,
قبل خمس سنوات مضت، قلت:
"If you want to liberate society,
"إذا أردت تحرير مجتمع ما ،
all you need is the Internet."
كل ما تحتاجه هو الإنترنت."
Today, I believe if we want to liberate society,
اليوم، أؤمن أننا إذا أردنا تحرير مجتمع ما،
we first need to liberate the Internet.
ينبغي علينا أولا تحرير الإنترنت.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)